<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods power and providence: shewed, in the miraculous preservation and deliverance of eight Englishmen, left by mischance in Green-land anno 1630. nine moneths and twelve dayes With a true relation of all their miseries, their shifts and hardship they were put to, their food, &amp;c. such as neither heathen nor Christian men ever before endured. With a description of the chiefe places and rarities of that barren and cold countrey. Faithfully reported by Edvvard Pellham, one of eight men aforesaid. As also with a map of Green-land.</title>
            <author>Pellham, Edward, fl. 1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 676:3, 1283:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods power and providence: shewed, in the miraculous preservation and deliverance of eight Englishmen, left by mischance in Green-land anno 1630. nine moneths and twelve dayes With a true relation of all their miseries, their shifts and hardship they were put to, their food, &amp;c. such as neither heathen nor Christian men ever before endured. With a description of the chiefe places and rarities of that barren and cold countrey. Faithfully reported by Edvvard Pellham, one of eight men aforesaid. As also with a map of Green-land.</title>
                  <author>Pellham, Edward, fl. 1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [1] p., folded plate : map  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Y[oung] for Iohn Partridge, and are to be sold at the signe of the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A2 is a cancel; the heading to the dedication includes Sir J. Merick. Variant: A2 is cancellandum, with heading omitting Merick's name.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Gods power in the preservation of eight men in Green-land.</note>
                  <note>The map is from the same plate as STC 20509, vol. 3, p. 472-3.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19566a on UMI microfilm reel 676.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 676 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy) and at reel 1293 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Greenland --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods Power and Providence:</hi> Shewed, IN THE MIRACV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Preſervation and Deliverance of eight Engliſhmen, left by miſchance in <hi>Green-land</hi> Anno 1630. nine moneths and twelve dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a true Relation of all their miſeries,</hi> their ſhifts and hardſhip they were put to, their food, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch as neither <hi>Heathen</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtian</hi> men ever before endured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Deſcription of the chiefe Places and</hi> Rarities of that barren and cold Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully reported by</hi> EDVVARD PELLHAM, one of the eight men aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo with a Map of</hi> GREEN-LAND.</p>
            <q>
               <p>They that goe downe into the Sea in ſhips; that doe buſineſſe in great waters:</p>
               <p>Theſe ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 107.23, 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Y.</hi> for IOHN PARTRIDGE, and are to be ſold at the Signe of the <hi>Sunne</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>modern bookplate</figDesc>
                  <head>ROBERT DAVIES of Lannerch Denbighshire</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:3"/>
            <head>To the right VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir HVGH HAMMERSLY Knight, Alderman of the Citie of London, Governour of the Worſhipfull Company of the Muſcovia Merchants: And to the VVorſhipfull, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman Freeman, Captaine William Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; And to all the reſt of the Worſhipfull Aſſiſtants and Adventurers in the ſaid famous Company. <hi>Edward Pellham</hi> dedicateth both this and his future Labours.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull and moſt famous Merchants:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He hard adventure my poore ſelfe and fellowes under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went in your Worſhips ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is a great deale plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanter for others to reade, than it was for us to endure. How ever hard, wee have now endured it; and if ever after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages
<pb facs="tcp:14702:4"/>ſhall ſpeake of it, (as the world ſtill doth of the <hi>Dutch-mens</hi> hard Winter in <hi>nova Zembla:</hi>) thus much of the Voyage ſhall redound to your honours, that it was done by your Servants. This may alſo returne to our Countreys good; That if the firſt inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Countrey by a Princes Subiects (which is the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> beſt title to his <hi>Indyes</hi>) doth take poſſeſſion of it for their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne:</hi> Then is <hi>Green-land</hi> by a ſecond right taken <hi>livery</hi> and <hi>Seiſin</hi> of, for his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> uſe; his Subiects being the firſt that ever did (and I beleeve the laſt that ever will) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite there. Many a rich returne may your Worſhips in generall, and the brave Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers in particular receive from this and all other places: and may your Servants be ever hereafter, warned to take heede by our harmes. God ſend your Worſhips long life, and much honour, and ſufficient wealth, to maintaine both. This is the hearty prayer of your Worſhips poore ſervant</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Pellham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader: That God may have the onely glory of this our deliverance, give mee leave to looke backe unto that voyage, which the <hi>Dutch-men</hi> made into <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> in the yeare <hi>1596.</hi> In which place, they having beene (like our ſelves) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken with the Winter, were there forced to ſtay it out as wee were. Which being an Action ſo famous all the world over, encouraged mee both to publiſh this of ours, as alſo now to draw out ſome compariſons with them: that ſo our deliverance, and Gods glory may appeare both the more gracious and the greater.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Nova Zembla</hi> ſtands in the Degree <hi>76.</hi> North latitude: our wintering place is in <hi>77.</hi> Degrees and <hi>40.</hi> Minutes, that is, almoſt two Degrees neerer the North <hi>Pole</hi> than they were; and ſo much therefore the colder. The <hi>Dutch</hi> were furniſhed with all things neceſſary both for <hi>life</hi> and <hi>health;</hi> had no want of any thing: <hi>Bread, Beere,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> they had good, and good ſtore. Victuals they had Gods plenty; and Apparell both for preſent clothing, and for ſhift too: and all this they brought with them in their Ship. We (God knowes)
<pb facs="tcp:14702:5"/>wanted all theſe. <hi>Bread, Beere,</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> we had none. As for meate, our greateſt and chiefeſt feeding was the <hi>Whale Frittars,</hi> and thoſe mouldie too; the loathſomeſt meate in the world. For our <hi>Veniſon,</hi> 'twas hard to finde, but a great deale harder to get: and for our third ſort of proviſion the <hi>Beares;</hi> 'twas a meaſuring caſt which ſhould be eaten firſt, <hi>Wee</hi> or the <hi>Beares,</hi> when we firſt ſaw one another; and we perceived by them, that they had as good hopes to devoure us, as wee to kill them. The <hi>Dutch</hi> kill'd Beares, 'tis true: but it was for their skinnes, not for their fleſh. The <hi>Dutch</hi> had a <hi>Surgeon</hi> in their Companie; wee none but the great <hi>Phyſician</hi> to take care and cure of us. They had the benefite of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and Purging:</hi> wee of neither. They had their Ship at hand to be-friend them; wee had here periſhed, had not other Ships fetcht us off. They had <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> wee no direction.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Dutch</hi> complained therefore of the extremity of the cold, (as well they might) and that when in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their houſe, they (as Carpenters uſe to doe) put the iron nayles into their mouthes, they there froze, and ſtucke ſo faſt, that they brought off the skinne and forced blood: how cold, thinke you, were we, that were faine to maintaine two fires, to keepe our very morter from free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. The <hi>Dutch</hi> complain'd, that their walls were fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen two inches thicke on the inſide for all their fire: and if ours were not ſo, 'twas our paines and induſtry at firſt in building. The <hi>Dutch-mens</hi> clothes froze upon their backes, and their ſhooes were like hornes upon their feete: but that was their owne ignorance; for they had Sea-coles enough with them, if they had knowne how to uſe them. If their drinke and Sacke were ſo hard fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen
<pb facs="tcp:14702:5"/>into lumps of yce, that they were faine to cut it out; how much harder was it for us, that were forced to make hot Irons our beſt toaſts to warme the ſnow withall, for our mornings draughts? They uſed heated ſtones and billets to their feete and bodies, to warme them: which, though an hard ſhift, yet was it better than we had any.</p>
            <p>Lay now all theſe together, the diſtance of place, wee being many miles more into the cold than they: the want both of meate and clothes; and that the houſe wee lived in, we had but three dayes reſpite to build for nine moneths to come; and then may the world ſee, that <hi>the Dutch had the better proviſions, and wee the abler bodies.</hi> If therefore the <hi>Dutch-mens</hi> deliverance were worthily accounted a wonder, ours can amount to little leſſe than a miracle. The greater therefore our deliverance, the greater muſt be Gods glory. And that's the Authors purpoſe in publiſhing of it. God keepe the Readers from the like dangers. So prayes he that endured what he here writes of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edw. Pellham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:6"/>
            <head>The names of the Men thus ſtaying in GREEN-LAND, for nine moneths and twelve dayes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VVIlliam Fakely,</hi> Gunner. <hi>Edward Pellham,</hi> Gunners mate, the Author of this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Iohn Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Robert Goodfellow,</hi> Sea-men. <hi>Thomas Ayers,</hi> Whale-cutter. <hi>Henry Bett,</hi> Cooper. <hi>Iohn Dawes,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kellet,</hi> Land-men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Greenland</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>A Whale is ordinarly about 60 foote longe</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>When the whale comes aboue water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhallop rowes towards him and being within reach of him the harpoiner darts his harpingiron at him out of both his hands and being faſt they lance him to death</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>The whale is cut up as hee lyes floting croſse the ſtearne of a ſhipp the blubber is cut from the fleſh by peeces 3 or 4 foote long and being raſed is rowed on ſhore towards the coppers</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>They place 2. or 3. coppers on a roe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chopping boat on the one ſide and the cooling boate on the other ſide to receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coppers, the chopt blubber being boyled is taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> out of the coppers and put in wiker baſkets or barowes throwg<hi rend="sup">h</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the oyle is dreaned and run<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cooler w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is fall of water out of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it is convaied by troughs into buts or hogſheads</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>The manner of killing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seamorces</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>The manner of kil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing Beares</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>The Seamorce is in quantity as bigg as an oxe</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>When the whale is killed hee is in this mann towed to the ſhipps by twoe or three ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops made fast one to another.</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>The peeces of blubber are towed to the ſhore ſide by a ſhallop and drawne on ſhore by a crane or caried by twoe menn on a barrowe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twoe cutters w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cutts them the breadt<hi rend="sup">h</hi> of a trencher and very thin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; by twoe boys are caried w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> handhooks to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choppers</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>Thus they make cleane and ſcrape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whale fins</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>A tent and Coopers at worke</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14702:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14702:8"/>
            <head>Gods Power and Providence in the preſervation of eight Men in GREEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, nine Moneths and twelve Dayes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>But wee had the ſentence of death in our ſelves, that wee ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the dead.</p>
                  <p>Who delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: in whom wee truſt that hee will yet deliver us.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Cor. 1. ver. 9, 10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>REENLAND is a Country ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry farre Northward, ſituated in 77. degrees, and 40. minutes, that is, within 12. degrees and 20. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of the very North Pole it ſelfe. The Land is wonderfull mountainous; the Mountaines all the year long full of yce and ſnow: the Plaines in part bare in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14702:9"/>time. There growes neither tree not hearbe in it, except <hi>Scurvygraſſe</hi> and <hi>Sorrell.</hi> The Sea is as barren as the Land, affording no fiſh but Whales, Sea-horſes, Seales, &amp; another ſmall fiſh. And hither there is a yearely Fleet of Engliſh ſent. Wee eight men therefore being employed in the ſervice of the Right Worſhipfull Company of <hi>Muſcowie</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, in the good ſhip called the <hi>Salutation</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> were bound for this <hi>Greenland</hi> aforeſaid, to make a voyage upon <hi>Whales</hi> or <hi>Sea-horſe,</hi> for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Merchants, and the good of the Common-wealth. Wee ſet ſayle from <hi>London</hi> the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> 1630. and having a faire gale, wee quickly left the fertile bankes of <hi>Englands</hi> pleaſant ſhoares behindeus. After which, ſetting our comely ſayles to this ſuppoſed proſperous gale, and ranging through the boyſterous billowes of the rugged Seas, by the helpe and gracious aſſiſtance of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, wee ſafely arrived at our deſired Port, in <hi>Greenland,</hi> the eleventh of <hi>Iune</hi> following. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon having moored our ſhips, and carryed our caske aſhoare, wee, with all expedition, fell to the fitting up of our Shallops, with all things neceſſarie for our intended voyage. Wee were in companie three Ships; all which were then appointed by the order of our Captaine, <hi>Captaine William Goodler,</hi> to ſtay at the <hi>Foreland,</hi> untill the fifteenth of <hi>Iuly;</hi> with reſolution, that if we could not by that time make a voyage according to our expectation, then, to ſend one ſhip to the Eaſtward, unto a fiſhing place ſome foureſcore leagues from thence; whither at the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the yeare, the Whales uſe more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14702:9"/>to reſort. A ſecond of the three ſhips was deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> (a place ſome fifteene leagues diſtant to the <hi>Southward</hi>) thereto trie her skill and fortune, if it were poſſible thereto make a voyage. The third ſhip (which was the ſame wherein wee were) was appointed to ſtay at the <hi>Fore-land,</hi> untill the twentieth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> But the Captaine having made a great voyage at <hi>Bell Sownd,</hi> diſpatches a Shallop towards our ſhip, with a command unto us to come to him at <hi>Bell Sownd</hi> aforeſaid: his purpoſe being, both to have us take in ſome of his <hi>Trane Oyle,</hi> as alſo by joyning our forces together, to make the Fleete ſo much the ſtronger for the defence of the Merchants goods homeward bound, the <hi>Dunkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> being very ſtrong and riſe at ſea in thoſe dayes. Upon the eighth day of <hi>Anguſt</hi> (thereupon) leaving the <hi>Foreland,</hi> wee directed our courſe to the <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> towards <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> thereto take in twenty of our men, which had out of ourſhips company beene ſent into the leſſer ſhip; for the furtherance of her voyage.</p>
            <p>But the winde being now contrary, our ſhip could no way <hi>lye our courſe.</hi> The fifteenth day, being calme and cleare, and our ſhip now in the <hi>Offing,</hi> ſome foure leagues from <hi>Blacke point,</hi> and about five from the <hi>Maydens pappes</hi> (which is a place famous, both for very good, and for great ſtore of <hi>Veniſon,</hi>) our Maſter ſent us eight men here named, altogether in a ſhallop for the hunting and killing of ſome Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for the ſhips proviſion. Wee thus leaving the ſhip, and having taken a brace of dogs along with us, and furniſh our ſelves with a ſnap-hance, two
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14702:10"/>lances, and a tinder-boxe; wee directed our courſe towards the ſhoare, where in foure houres wee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, the weather being at that time faire and cleare, and every way ſeaſonable for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of our preſent intentions. That day we laid fourteene tall and nimble Deere along; and being very weary and throughly tyred, firſt with rowing, and now with hunting, wee fell to eate ſuch victuals as wee had brought along, agreeing to take our reſt for that night, and the next day to make an end of our hunting, and ſo fairely to returne to our ſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. But the next day, as it pleaſed God, the weather falling out ſomething thicke, and much yce in the <hi>Offing</hi> betwixt the ſhoare and the ſhip (by reaſon of a Southerly winde driving alongſt the coaſt) our ſhip was forced ſo farre to <hi>ſtand off</hi> into the Sea, to be cleare of they yce, that wee had quite loſt the fight of her: neither could wee aſſure our ſelves, whether ſhee were incloſed in the drift yce, or not: and the weather ſtill growing thicker and thicker, we thought it our beſt courſe to hunt alongſt the ſhoare, and ſo to goe for <hi>Greene-harbour,</hi> there to ſtay aboard the ſhip with the reſt of our men, vntill our own ſhip ſhould come into the Port.</p>
            <p>Coaſting thus along towards <hi>Greene-harbour,</hi> wee kill'd eight Deere more; and ſo at laſt having well loaden our Shallop with Veniſon, wee ſtill kept on our courſe towards <hi>Green-harbour:</hi> where arriving upon the ſeventeenth day, wee found (to our great wonderment) that the ſhip was departed thence, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with our twenty men aforeſaid. That which increaſed our admiration was, for that wee knew
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14702:10"/>they had not victuals ſufficient aboard, to ſerve them (by proportion) homewards bownd: which made vs againe to wonder what ſhould be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their ſo ſudden departure.</p>
            <p>Perceiving our ſelves thus fruſtrated of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and having now but bare three dayes (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to appointment) to the uttermoſt expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our limited time for our departure out of the Country; we thought it our beſt courſe to make all poſſible ſpeed to get to <hi>Bell Sownd,</hi> unto our Captaine, fearing that a little delay might bring a great deale of danger. For the lightening therefore of our Shallop, that ſhe might make the better way through the waters, wee heaved our Veniſon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and caſt it all into the Sea. Having thus forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> with a longing deſire to recover <hi>Bell Sownd</hi> (from thence diſtant ſome ſixteene leagues to the <hi>Southward</hi>) that night wee got halfe way about the point of the <hi>Neſſe,</hi> or point of land, called <hi>Low-Neſſe:</hi> But the darkneſſe or miſtie fogge increaſing ſo faſt upon us, that it was impoſſible for us to get further; even there betweene two rocks we <hi>coved</hi> from the ſeventeenth day at night, untill the eighteenth day at noone. At which time the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being ſomewhat clearer (though very thicke ſtill) wee left the <hi>Neſſe</hi> behinde us, ſtill deſirous to recover <hi>Bell Sownd:</hi> but having never a <hi>Compaſſe</hi> to direct our courſe by, nor any of our company that was <hi>Pilot</hi> ſufficient to know the land when he ſaw it, we were faine to grabble in the darke (as it were) like a blinde man for his way, and ſo over-ſhot <hi>Bell point</hi> at leaſt tenne leagues to the <hi>Southward,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14702:11"/>
               <hi>Horne Sownd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of us in the meane time knowing that it was impoſſible to bee ſo long a rowing and ſayling of eight leagues (for wee did both row and ſayle) made enquirie, <hi>How the Harbour lay in?</hi> whereunto there was a ready anſwer made, <hi>That it lay Eaſt in.</hi> Taking the matter therefore into our better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, ſome of us judged, that it could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be further to the <hi>Southward</hi> (our reaſon being, our obſervation of the lands <hi>rounding away</hi> and <hi>trenting</hi> towards the <hi>Eaſtward</hi>) and reſolved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to row no further on that Courſe, for the finding of <hi>Bell Sownd.</hi> And though wee were againe perſwaded by <hi>William Fakely</hi> our Gunner, (a proper Sea-man, though no skilfull Mariner, who had been in the Country five or ſixe times before, which none of our Sea-men had beene) that it was further to the <hi>Southwards:</hi> yet we, truſting better to our own reaſons than unto his perſwaſions, againe returned towards the <hi>Northward:</hi> which was our beſt and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteſt Courſe indeed, for the finding of <hi>Bell Sownd.</hi> Steering of which Courſe, wee were now come within two miles of <hi>Bell Point;</hi> &amp; the weather being faire and cleare, wee preſently deſcryed the tops of the loftie mountaines. <hi>William Fakely</hi> thereupon looking about him, preſently cries out unto us, <hi>That wee were all this while upon a wrong Courſe:</hi> upon hearing of which words, ſome of our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie (yea the moſt) were perſwaded, to <hi>wend</hi> about the Boates head the ſecond time, unto the <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards:</hi> which one action was the maine and onely cauſe of our too late repentance, though for mine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14702:11"/>owne part (as it is well knowne) I never gave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto their counſell.</p>
            <p>And thus upon the fatall twentieth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (which was the utmoſt day of our limited time for ſtaying in the Country) wee againe returned the quite contrary way, namely to the <hi>Southward.</hi> Thus utterly uncertaine when and where to finde the <hi>Sownd;</hi> a thouſand ſadde imaginations overtooke our perplexed minds, all of us aſſuredly knowing, that a million of miſeries would of neceſſitie enſue, if wee found not the ſhips, whereby to ſave our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. In this diſtracted time of our thoughts, wee were now againe the ſecond time runne as farre to the <hi>Southward</hi> as at the firſt: and finding by all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereupon, how that there was no likelihood at all of finding any ſuch place further to the <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> we <hi>wended</hi> the Shallop the ſecond time unto the <hi>Northward. William Fakely</hi> hereupon, being unwilling to condeſcend unto our agreement, ſtill perſwaded us, that <hi>That could not poſsibly bee our Courſe:</hi> but we not truſting any longer unto his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull perſwaſions, (though all in him was out of good will, and ſtrong conceit of his being in the rights) bent our Courſe to the <hi>Northward;</hi> and hee not conſenting to ſteere any longer, I tooke the Oare out of his hand to ſteere any longer, I tooke the Oare out of his hand to ſteere the Boate withall. The weather all this while continued faire and cleare, and it pleaſed God at the very inſtant time, to ſend the winde <hi>Eaſterly:</hi> which advantage wee thankfully apprehending, preſently ſet ſayle. The winde increaſed freſh and large, and our Shallop ſwiftly running, we arrived the one and twentieth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14702:12"/>day at <hi>Bell point,</hi> where wee found the winde right out of the <hi>Sownd</hi> at <hi>Eaſt Northeaſt</hi> ſo fiercely blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that we could not poſſibly row to <hi>Wind-wards;</hi> but being forced to take in our ſayle, we were faine to betake our ſelves unto our Oares, by helpe of which wee recovered ſome two miles within the ſhoare, where we were conſtrained for that time to <hi>Cove,</hi> or elſe to drive to <hi>Lee-wards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus finding this to be the very place we had all this while ſought for, (he now alſo agreeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) we forth with ſought out and found an harbor for our <hi>Shallop:</hi> and having brought <hi>her</hi> thereinto, two of our men were preſently diſpatched over land unto the <hi>Tent</hi> at <hi>Bell Sownd,</hi> to ſee if the Ships were ſtill there; of which, by reaſon of the times being expired, and the opportunitie of the preſent faire winde, wee were much afraid. The <hi>Tent</hi> being diſtant ten miles at the leaſt from our Shallop, our men at their comming thither finding the ſhips to be departed out of the Roade, and not being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, whether or not they might be at <hi>Bottle Cove,</hi> (three leagues diſtant on the other ſide of the <hi>Sownd</hi>) riding there under the <hi>Loome</hi> of the land; againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto us with this ſadde newes. The ſtorme of winde hitherto continuing, about mid-night fell ſtarke calme: whereupon we, unwilling to loſe our firſt opportunity, departed towards <hi>Bottle Cove;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt hope and feare of finding the ſhips there: whither comming the two &amp; twentieth, and finding the ſhips departed, we, having neither <hi>Pilot, Plat,</hi> nor <hi>Compaſſe</hi> for our directors to the <hi>Eaſtward,</hi> found our ſelves (God he knoweth) to have little
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14702:12"/>hope of any delivery out of that apparent danger. Our feares increaſed upon us, even whil'ſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted whether it were ſafeſt for us either to goe or ſtay. If goe, then thought wee upon the dangers in ſayling, by reaſon of the much yce in the way; as alſo of the difficultie in finding the place, when wee ſhould come thereabouts. If we reſolved ſtill to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine at <hi>Bell Sownd,</hi> then wee thought that no other thing could be looked for, but a miſerable and a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning death, ſeeing there appeared no poſſibility of inhabiting there, or to endure ſo long, ſo darkſome, and ſo bitter a winter.</p>
            <p>And thus were our thoughts at that time diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, thus were our feares increaſed; nor were they cauſeleſſe feares altogether. Well, wee knew that neither <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Heathen</hi> people, had ever before inhabited thoſe deſolate and untemperate <hi>Clymates.</hi> This alſo, to increaſe our feares, had wee certainly heard; how that the <hi>Merchants</hi> having in former times much deſired, and that with proffer of great rewards for the hazarding of their lives, and of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient furniture and proviſion of all things that might bee thought neceſſary for ſuch an underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, to any that would adventure to winter in thoſe parts; could never yet finde any ſo hardy, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their lives unto ſo hazardous an undertaking: yea notwithſtanding theſe proffers had beene made both unto Mariners of good experience, and of noble reſolutions, and alſo unto divers other bold ſpirits; yet had the action of wintering in thoſe parts, never by any beene hitherto undertaken. This alſo had we heard, how that the company of <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covie
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14702:13"/>Merchants,</hi> having once procured the reprive of ſome malefactors, that had here at home beene convicted by Law for ſome haynous crimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and that both with promiſe of pardon for their faults, and with addition of rewards alſo, if ſo be they would undertake to remaine in <hi>Green-land</hi> but one whole yeare, and that every way provided for too, both of Clothes, Victuals, and all things elſe, that might any way be needfull for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: Theſe poore wretches hearing of this large proffer, &amp; fearing preſent execution at home, reſolved to make tryall of the adventure. The time of yeare being come, and the ſhips ready to depart, theſe condemned creatures are imbarked, who after a certaine ſpace there arriving, and taking a view of the deſolateneſſe of the place; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch a horrour and inward feare in their hearts, as that they reſolved rather to returne for <hi>England</hi> to make ſatisfaction with their lives for their former faults committed, than there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, though with aſſured hope of gaining their pardon: Inſomuch as the time of the yeare being come, that the ſhips were to depart from theſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſhoares, they made knowne their full intent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Captaine: who being a pittifull and a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Gentleman, would not by force conſtraine them to ſtay in that place, which was ſo contrary to their minds; but having made his voyage by the time expired; hee againe imbarked and brought them over with him into <hi>England;</hi> where, through the interceſſion and meanes of the Worſhipfull Companie of <hi>Muſcovie</hi> Merchants, they eſcaped
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14702:13"/>that death, which they had before beene condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto. The remembrance of theſe two former ſtories, as alſo of a third (more terrible than both the former, for that it was likely to be our own caſe) more miſerably now affrighted us: and that was the lamentable and unmanly ends of nine good and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, left in the ſame place heretofore by the ſelfe ſame Maſter that now left us behinde: who all dyed miſerably upon the place, being cruelly disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured after their deaths by the ſavage Beares and hungry Foxes, which are not onely the civileſt, but alſo the onely inhabitants of that comfortleſſe Countrey: the lamentable ends and miſcarriage of which men, had beene enough indeed to have daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſpirits of the moſt noble reſolution.</p>
            <p>All theſe fearefull examples preſenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before our eyes, at this place of <hi>Bottle Cove</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, made us, like amazed men, to ſtand looking one upon another, all of us, as it were, beholding in the preſent, the future calamities both of himſelfe and of his fellowes. And thus, like men already me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſed into the yce of the Country, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſt both our ſenſe and reaſon; ſtood wee with the eyes of pittie beholding one another.</p>
            <p>Nor was it other mens examples and miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and feares alone, that made us amazed, but it was the conſideration of our want of all neceſſary proviſion for the life of man, that already ſtrooke us to the heart: For we were not only unprovided, both of clothes to keepe us warme, and of foode to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the wrath of cruell famine: but vtterly deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute alſo wee were of a ſufficient houſe, wherein to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14702:14"/>ſhrowd and ſhelter our ſelves from the chilling cold. Thus for a ſpace ſtanding all mute and ſilent, weighing with our ſelves the miſerie wee were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fallen into, and knowing delay in theſe extremities to be the mother of all dangers, we began to conceive hope, even out of the depth of deſpaire. Rowſing up our benummed ſenſes therefore, wee now lay out heads and counſels together, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke our ſelves of the likelieſt courſe for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation in that place; ſeeing that all hopes of gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our paſſage into <hi>England,</hi> were then quite fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Shaking off therefore all childiſh and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate feares, it pleaſed God to give us hearts like men, to arme our ſelves with a reſolution to doe our beſt for the reſiſting of that monſter of Deſperation. An agreement thereupon by a generall conſent of the whole Companie we then entred into, to take the opportunity of the next faire weather, and goe for <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> to hunt and kill Veniſon for part of our winter proviſion.</p>
            <p>Having thus agreed amongſt ourſelves, the five and twentieth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the weather and wind being both faire, wee direct our courſe towards <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> ſome ſixteene leagues (as I before told you) diſtant from <hi>Bell Sownd:</hi> and the winde being freſh and faire, within the ſpace of twelve houres we there arrived. Upon which place being now landed, the firſt thing we did, was to make us a Tent with the ſayle of our Shallop, pitcht up and ſpread upon our Oares; a ſorry one (God knowes) though it were, yet under it we reſolved to reſt our ſelves that night, to refreſh our bodies with ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14702:14"/>food as wee there had, and the next day to returne againe unto our hunting. The weather that night proving faire and cleare, wee made our ſleepe the ſhorter: (and alas what men could ſleepe in ſuch an extremitie!) and fitting our ſelves and Shallop the beſt we might, to <hi>Coles Parke</hi> we went, a place ſome two leagues diſtant from us, and well knowne unto <hi>Thomas Ayers,</hi> that was one of our Companie, to be well ſtored with Veniſon. Comming a-ſhoare at which place, though we found not ſo many Deere as we indeed expected, yet ſeven we killed the ſame day, and foure Beares to boote; which wee alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to eate.</p>
            <p>But the weather beginning now to overcaſt, and not likely to continue good for hunting; wee that night returned againe unto <hi>Green-harbour:</hi> where making us a Tent of our <hi>Sayle</hi> and <hi>Oares</hi> (as is before deſcribed) we fell to eate of ſuch meate as God had ſent us, and betooke our ſelves to our reſt upon it. Having reſted ourſelves a while, and now finding the weather to cleare up, we broke off our ſleepe for that time, fitting our ſelves and two dogges againe to goe a hunting; leaving <hi>William Fakely</hi> and <hi>Iohn Dawes</hi> behinde us in the Tent at <hi>Green-harbour,</hi> as our Cookes (for the time) to dreſſe ſome meate that wee had, for our refreſhment at our returne.</p>
            <p>Departing thus from the Tent, wee rowed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Coles Parke;</hi> in the way whither, upon the ſide of a hill, by the Sea ſide, wee eſpyed ſeven Deere feeding, whereupon preſently a-ſhoare we went, and with our Dogs kill'd ſixe of them, after which, the weather againe overcaſting, wee thought it to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14702:15"/>little purpoſe to goe any further at that time, but reſolved to hunt all along the ſide of that hill, and ſo at night to returne unto our Tent. Going thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, wee kill'd ſixe Deere more; which wee had no ſooner done, but it began to blow and raine, and to be very darke: whereupon wee haſted towards the Tent, there intending to refreſh our ſelves with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals and with reſt for that night, and the next day to returne againe unto our hunting. This purpoſe of ours was by the foule weather the next day hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: for it fell ſo blacke, ſo cold, and ſo windy, that we found it no way fitting for our purpoſe. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therefore our owne Shallop with <hi>Beares</hi> and <hi>Veniſon;</hi> and another Shallop which we there found haled up, and left by the Ships Companie, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeare they uſe to doe: lading this other Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, I ſay, with the <hi>Graves</hi> of the <hi>Whales</hi> that had beene there boyled this preſent yeare, (which wee there found in heapes flung upon the ground) wee, dividing our ſelves into two equall companies, that is to ſay, <hi>William Fakely</hi> with one <hi>Sea-man</hi> and two <hi>Land-men</hi> with him, betaking themſelves unto one Shallop; and <hi>Edward Pellham</hi> with another <hi>Sea-man</hi> and two <hi>Land-men</hi> more with him, going into the other Shallop; wee all committed our ſelves unto the Sea, intending with the next faire weather to goe to <hi>Bell Sownd</hi> unto our Tent: which was the place wee ſet up our Reſt upon, to remaine at all the Winter.</p>
            <p>Towards <hi>Bell Sownd</hi> therefore we went, with a purpoſe there to lay up our Store of what victuals wee had already gotten together; and with the next
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14702:15"/>faire winde to come hither againe, to trie if it were poſſible for us there to provide our ſelves of ſome more Veniſon for our Winter proviſion.</p>
            <p>Having thus laden both our Shallops, appointed our Companie, and all ready now for our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; wee were overtaken with the night, and there forced to ſtay upon the place. The next day was <hi>Sunday;</hi> wherefore wee thought it fit to ſanctifie the <hi>Reſt</hi> of it, and to ſtay our ſelves there untill <hi>Munday,</hi> and to make the beſt uſe we could of that good day, taking the beſt courſe wee could for the ſerving of God Almighty; although we had not ſo much as a Booke amongſt us all, the whole time that wee ſtaid in that Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sabbath</hi> day being ſhut up by the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing night, we betooke our ſelves to our Reſt: ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing untill the Sunne awakened us by his beginning to ſhew himſelfe upon the <hi>Munday</hi> morning. The day was no ſooner peept, but up we got, fitting our ſelves and buſineſſe for our departure. The weather was faire and cleere at the firſt; but after ſome foure houres rowing, the skie began ſo to over taſt, and the winde to blow ſo hard, that we could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly get to <hi>Bell Sownd</hi> that night, but <hi>Coved</hi> halfe way, untill the next morning; at which time we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <hi>Bottle Cove.</hi> To which place when wee were once come, we found the winde (then at <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt</hi>) to blow ſo hard, that it was impoſſible for us to reach <hi>Bell Sownd,</hi> but were forced to ſtay at <hi>Bottle Cove</hi> for that night. Our Shallops we made faſt one unto another, with a Rope faſtning the <hi>head</hi> of the one unto the <hi>ſterne</hi> of the other; and ſo caſting our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14702:16"/>
               <hi>Grabnell</hi> or <hi>Anchor</hi> over-board, we left them riding in the <hi>Cove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſee now what a miſchance, for the tryall of our patience, and for the making of us to relye more upon his providence, than upon any outward meanes of our owne; God now ſuffered to befall us: We being now all a-ſhore, the <hi>Southweſt</hi> winde blew ſo hard and right into the <hi>Cove,</hi> that it made the Sea go <hi>high;</hi> our Anchor alſo <hi>comming home</hi> at the ſame time, both our Shallops caſting alongſt the ſhoare, ſunke preſently in the Sea: wetting by this meanes our whole proviſion, the weather with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all beating ſome of it out of the Boates, which wee found ſwimming up and downe the ſhoare. For, comming out of our Tent in the meane time, judge you what a ſight this was unto us, to ſee by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, the beſt part of our proviſion (the onely hope of our lives) to be in danger utterly to be loſt, (or at leaſt ſpoyled with the Sea-water,) for which we had taken ſuch paines, and run ſuch adventures in the getting. In this our miſerie wee ſaw no way but one (and that a very deſperate one) namely, to runne preſently into the <hi>high-wrought</hi> Sea, getting by that meanes into our Shallops to ſave the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of our proviſions, ready now to be waſht quite away by the billowes. A <hi>Halſer</hi> thereupon we got, which faſtning unto our Shallops, wee, with a <hi>Crabbe</hi> or <hi>Capſtang,</hi> by maine force of hand heaved them out of the water upon the ſhoare. This done, all along the Sea ſide we goe; ſeeking there and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up ſuch of our proviſions, as were ſwumme away from our Shallops. Having by this meanes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14702:16"/>gleaned up all that could be gotten together, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from thenceforth to let our Boates lye upon the ſhoare, till ſuch time as the weather ſhould prove faire and better; and then to goe over unto <hi>Bell Sownd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third of <hi>September</hi> the weather proving faire and good, we forthwith lanched our Shallops into the water, and in them wee that day got into <hi>Bell Sownd.</hi> Thither ſo ſoone as we were come, our firſt buſineſſe was, to take our proviſion out of our Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops into the Tent: our next, to take a particular view of the place, and of the great Tent eſpecially; as being the place of our habitation for the enſuing Winter. This which we call the <hi>Tent,</hi> was a kinde of houſe (indeed) built of Timber and Boards very ſubſtantially, and covered with Flemiſh Tyles: by the men of which nation it had in the time of their trading thither, beene builded. Foureſcore foot long it is, and in breadth fiftie. The uſe of it was for the <hi>Coopers,</hi> employed for the ſervice of the <hi>Company,</hi> to worke, lodge, and live in, all the while they make caske for the putting up of the Trane Oyle. Our view being taken, we found the weather beginning to alter ſo ſtrangely, and the nights and froſts ſo to grow upon us, that wee durſt not adventure upon another hunting voyage unto <hi>Green-harbour;</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Sownd</hi> would be ſo frozen, that wee ſhould never be able to get backe to our Tent againe. By land it was (we knew) in vaine for us to thinke of returning: for the land is ſo mountainous, that there is no travelling that way.</p>
            <p>Things being at this paſſe with us, we bethought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14702:17"/>our ſelves of building another ſmaller <hi>Tent</hi> with all expedition: the place muſt of neceſſity be within the greater Tent. With our beſt wits therefore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a view of the place, we reſolved upon the <hi>South</hi> ſide. Taking downe another leſſer Tent therefore, (built for the <hi>Land-men</hi> hard by the other, wherein in time of yeare they lay whileſt they made their Oyle) from thence we fetcht our materials. That Tent furniſht us with 150 <hi>Deale-boards,</hi> beſides <hi>Poſts</hi> or <hi>Stancheons,</hi> and <hi>Rafters.</hi> From three <hi>Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys</hi> of the <hi>Furnaces</hi> wherein they uſed to boyle their <hi>Oyles,</hi> wee brought a thouſand Bricks: there alſo found wee three Hogſheads of very fine <hi>Lyme,</hi> of which ſtuffe wee alſo fetcht another Hogſhead from <hi>Bottle Cove,</hi> on the other ſide of the <hi>Sownd,</hi> ſome three leagues diſtant. Mingling this Lyme with the Sand of the Sea ſhore, we made very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent good morter for the laying of our Bricks: fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to worke whereupon, the weather was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame cold, as that we were faine to make two fires to keepe our morter from freezing. <hi>William Fakely</hi> and my ſelfe undertaking the <hi>Maſonrie,</hi> began to raiſe a wall of one bricke thickneſſe, againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner planks of the ſide of the Tent. Whileſt we were laying of theſe Bricks, the reſt of our Companie were otherwiſe employed every one of them: ſome in taking them downe, others in making of them cleane, and in bringing them in baskets into the Tent: Some in making morter, and hewing of boards to build the other ſide withall: and two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers all the while, in flaying of our Veniſon. And thus having built the two outermoſt ſides of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14702:17"/>Tent with Bricks and Morter, and our Bricks now almoſt ſpent, wee were enforc't to build the other two ſides with Boards; and that in this manner. Firſt, we nayl'd our Deale boards on one ſide of the <hi>Poſt</hi> or <hi>Stancheon,</hi> to the thickneſſe of one foot; and on the other ſide in like manner: and ſo filling up the hollow place betweene with ſand, it became ſo tight and warme, as not the leaſt breath of ayre could poſſibly annoy us: Our Chimneys vent was into the greater Tent; being the breadth of one deale board, and foure foot long. The length of this our Tent was twenty foot, and the breadth ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene; the heighth tenne: our ſeeling being Deale boards five or ſixe times double, the middle of one, joyning ſo cloſe to the ſhut of the other, that no winde could poſſibly get betweene. As for our doore, beſides our making it ſo cloſe as poſſibly it could ſhut; we lined it moreover with a bed that we found lying there, which came over both the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening and the ſhutting of it. As for windowes, we made none at all: ſo that our light wee brought in through the greater Tent, by removing two or three tyles in the caves, which light came to us through the vent of our Chimney. Our next worke was, to ſet up foure Cabbins, billetting our ſelves two and two in a Cabbine. Our beds were the Deeres skinnes dryed, which wee found to be extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary warme, and a very comfortable kinde of lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to us in our diſtreſſe. Our next care then was for firing to dreſſe our meate withall, and for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the cold. Examinging therefore all the Shallops that had beene left a-ſhoare there by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14702:18"/>Ships, we found ſeven of them very crazie, and not ſerviceable for the next yeare. Thoſe wee made bold withall; brake them vp, and carried them into our houſe, <hi>ſtowing</hi> them over the beames in manner of a floore; intending alſo to <hi>ſtow</hi> the reſt of our firing over them, ſo to make the outer <hi>Tent</hi> the warmer, and to keepe withall the ſnow from dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving through the tyles into the Tent: which ſnow would otherwiſe have covered every thing, and have hindered us in comming at what wee wanted. When the weather was now growne cold, and the dayes ſhort, (or rather no dayes at all) wee made bold to <hi>ſtave</hi> ſome emptie Caske that were there left the yeare before: to the quantitie of 100 Tunne at leaſt. We alſo made uſe of ſome planks, and of two old Coolers (wherein they cool'd their Oyle) and of whatſoever might well bee ſpared, without damnifying of the voyage the next yeare. Thus having gotten together all, the firing that wee could poſſibly make, except we would make ſpoyle of the <hi>Shallops</hi> and <hi>Coolers</hi> that were there; which might eaſily have overthrowne the next yeares voyage, to the great hinderance of the Worſhipfull Companie, whoſe ſervants we being, were every way carefull of their profite. Comparing therefore the ſamll quantitie of our wood, together with the coldneſſe of the weather, and the length of time that there wee were likely to abide; wee caſt about to husband our ſtocke as thriftily as wee could, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to trie a new concluſion: Our tryall was this. When wee rak't up our fire at night, with a good quantitie of aſhes and of embers, wee put into the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14702:18"/>midd'ſt of it a piece of Elmen wood: where after it had laine ſixteene houres, we at our opening of it found great ſtore of fire upon it; whereupon wee made a common practice of it ever after. It never went out in eight moneths together or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Having thus provided both our <hi>houſe</hi> and <hi>firing;</hi> upon the twelfth of <hi>September</hi> a ſmall quantity of drift yce, came driving to and fro in the <hi>Sownd.</hi> Early in the morning therefore wee aroſe, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every where abroad, we at laſt eſpyed two <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſes</hi> lying a-ſleepe upon a piece of yce: preſently thereupon taking up an old <hi>Harping</hi> Iron that there lay in the Tent, &amp; faſtning a <hi>Grapnell</hi> Roape unto it, out lanch't wee our Boate to row towards them. Comming ſomething neere them, wee perceived them to be faſt a-ſleepe: which my ſelfe, then ſteer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Boate, firſt perceiving, ſpake to the rowers to hold ſtill their Oares, for feare of awaking them with the craſhing of the yce; and I, skulling the Boate eaſily along, came ſo neere at length unto them, that the Shallops even touch't one of them. At which inſtant <hi>William Fakely</hi> being ready with his <hi>Harping Iron,</hi> heav'd it ſo ſtrongly into the <hi>old one,</hi> that hee quite diſturbed her of her reſt: after which ſhee receiving five or ſixe thruſts with our lances, fell into a ſounder ſleepe of death. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpatch't the <hi>old one,</hi> the <hi>younger</hi> being loath to leave her damme, continued ſwimming ſo long about our Boate, that with our lances wee kill'd her alſo. Haling them both after this into the Boate, we rowed a-ſhoare, flayed our <hi>Sea-horſes,</hi> cut them in pieces, to roaſt and eate them. The nineteenth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14702:19"/>of the ſame moneth we ſaw other <hi>Sea-horſes,</hi> ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo in like manner upon ſeverall pieces of yce: but the weather being cold, they deſired not to ſleepe ſo much as before; and therefore could wee kill but one of them: of which one being right glad, we returned againe into our Tent.</p>
            <p>The nights at this time, and the cold weather increaſed ſo faſt upon us, that wee were out of all hopes of getting any more foode before the next Spring: our onely hopes were, to kill a <hi>Beare</hi> now and then, that might by chance wander that way. The next day therefore taking an exacter ſurvey of all our victuals, and finding our proportion too ſmall by halfe, for our time and companie; wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among our ſelves to come to <hi>Allowance,</hi> that is, to ſtint our ſelves to one reaſonable meale a day, and to keepe <hi>Wedneſdayes</hi> and <hi>Fridayes Faſting</hi> dayes;<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eaps of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>t of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ale, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e flung away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er the Oyle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gotten out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it.</note> excepting from the*. <hi>Frittars</hi> or <hi>Graves</hi> of the <hi>Whale</hi> (a very loathſome meane) of which we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed our ſelves ſufficient to ſuffice our preſent hunger: and at this dyet we continued ſome three moneths or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Having by this time finiſhed what ever we poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly could invent, for our preſervations in that deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late deſert; our clothes &amp; ſhooes alſo were ſo worne and torne (all to pieces almoſt) that wee muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity invent ſome new device for their reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Of <hi>Roape-yarne</hi> therefore, we made us <hi>thread,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Whale-bones needles</hi> to ſew our clothes withall. The nights were wax't very long, and by the tenth of <hi>October</hi> the cold ſo violent, that the Sea was frozen over: which had beene enough to haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14702:19"/>daunted the moſt aſſured reſolutions. At which time our buſineſſe being over, and nothing now to exerciſe our mindes upon; our heads began then to be troubled with a thouſand ſorts of imaginations. Then had wee leiſure (more than enough) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine our ſelves of our preſent and moſt miſerable conditions. Then had wee time to bewaile our wives and children at home; and to imagine what newes our unfortunate miſcarriages muſt needes be unto them. Then thought wee of our parents alſo, and what a cutting Coraſive it would be to them, to heare of the untimely deaths of their children. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles againe, wee revive our ſelves with ſome comfort, that our friends might take, in hoping that it might pleaſe <hi>God</hi> to preſerve us (even in this poore eſtate) untill the next yeare. Sometimes did we varie our griefes; complaining one while of the cruelty of our <hi>Maſter,</hi> that would offer to leave us to theſe diſtreſſes: and then preſently againe fell wee, not onely to excuſe him, but to lament both him and his companie, fearing they had beene overtaken by the yce, and miſerably that way periſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus tormented in mind with our doubts, our feares, and our griefes; and in our bodies with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cold, and wants; that hideous monſter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation, began now to preſent his uglieſt ſhape unto us: he now purſued us, hee now laboured to ſeize upon us. Thus finding our ſelves in a <hi>Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> as it were, of a perpetuall miſerie, wee thought it not beſt to give too much way unto our griefes; fearing, they alſo would moſt of all have wrought upon our weakeneſſe. Our prayers we now redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14702:20"/>unto the <hi>Almighty,</hi> for ſtrength and patience, in theſe our miſeries: and the <hi>Lord</hi> graciouſly liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto us, and granted theſe our petitions. By <hi>his</hi> aſſiſtance therefore, wee ſhooke off theſe thoughts, and cheer'd up our ſelves againe, to uſe the beſt meanes for our preſervations.</p>
            <p>Now therefore began we to thinke upon our <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon,</hi> and the preſerving of that; and how to order our <hi>firing</hi> in this cold weather. For feare therefore our <hi>firing</hi> ſhould faile us at the end of the yeare, we thought beſt to roaſt every day halfe a <hi>Deere,</hi> and to <hi>ſtow</hi> it in hogſheads. Which wee putting now in practice, wee forthwith filled three Hogſheads and an halfe; leaving ſo much raw, as would ſerve to roaſt every Sabbath day a quarter: and ſo for <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day, and the like.</p>
            <p>This concluſion being made amongſt us; then fell wee againe to bethinke us of our miſeries, both paſſed and to come: and how, (though if it pleaſed God to give us life, yet ſhould) we live as baniſhed men, not onely from our friends, but from all other companie. Then thought we of the pinching cold, and of the pining hunger: theſe were our thoughts, this our diſcourſe to paſſe away the time withall. But as if all this miſerie had beene too little, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently found another increaſe of it: For, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our proviſions once more, wee found that all our <hi>Frittars</hi> of the <hi>Whale</hi> were almoſt ſpoyled with the wet that they had taken: after which by lying ſo cloſe together, they were now growne mouldie: And our <hi>Beare</hi> and <hi>Veniſon</hi> we perceived againe not to amount to ſuch a quantity, as to allow us five
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14702:20"/>meales a weeke: whereupon we were faine to ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our ſtomacks of one meale more: ſo that for the ſpace of three moneths after that, we for foure dayes in the weeke fed upon the unſavory and mouldie <hi>Frittars,</hi> and the other three, we feaſted it with <hi>Beare</hi> and <hi>Veniſon.</hi> But as if it were not enough for us to want meate, we now began to want light alſo: all our meales proved ſuppers now; for little light could we ſee; even the glorious Sunne (as if unwilling to behold our miſeries) masking his love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly face from us, under the ſable vaile of cole-blacke night. Thus from the fourteenth of <hi>October,</hi> till the third of <hi>February,</hi> we never ſaw the <hi>Sunne;</hi> nor did hee all that time, ever ſo much as peepe above the <hi>Horizon.</hi> But the <hi>Moone</hi> we ſaw at all times, day and night (when the cloudes obſcured her not) ſhining as bright as ſhee doth in <hi>England.</hi> The Skie, 'tis true, is very much troubled with thicke and blacke weather all the Winter time: ſo that then, we could not ſee the <hi>Moone,</hi> nor could diſcerne what point of the Compaſſe ſhee bore upon us. A kinde of day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light wee had indeed, which glimmer'd ſome eight houres a day unto us; in <hi>October</hi> time I meane: for from thence unto the firſt of <hi>December,</hi> even that light was ſhortened tenne or twelve <hi>minuts</hi> a day conſtantly: ſo that from the firſt of <hi>December</hi> till the twentieth, there appeared no light at all; but all was one continued night. All that wee could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive was, that in a cleare ſeaſon now and then, there appeared a little glare of white, like ſome ſhow of day towards the <hi>South:</hi> but no light at all. And this continued till the firſt of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> by which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14702:21"/>time wee might perceive the day a little to increaſe. All this darkeſome time, no certainety could wee have when it ſhould be day, or when night: onely my ſelfe out of mine owne little judgement, kept the obſervation of it thus. Firſt bearing in minde the number of the <hi>Epact,</hi> I made my addition by a day ſuppoſed, (though not abſolutely to be known, by reaſon of the darkneſſe) by which I judged of the age of the <hi>Moone:</hi> and this gave me my rule of the paſſing of the time; ſo that at the comming of the Ships into the <hi>Port,</hi> I told them the very day of the moneth, as directly as they themſelves could tell mee.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of this darkeſome, irkeſome time, wee ſought ſome meanes of preſerving light amongſt us: finding therefore a piece of <hi>Sheete-lead</hi> over a ſeame of one of the Coolers; that we ript off, and made three Lampes of it: which maintaining with <hi>Oyle</hi> that wee found in the Coopers Tent, and <hi>Roape-yarne</hi> ſerving us in ſteed of Candle-weekes, wee kept them continually burning. And this was a great comfort to us in our extremity. Thus did we our beſt to preſerve our ſelves; but all this could not ſecure us: for wee in our owne thoughts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted our ſelves but dead men; and that our Tent was then our darkeſome dungeon, and we did but waite our day of tryall by our judge, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee ſhould live or dye. Our extremities being ſo many, made us ſometimes in impatient ſpeeches to breake forth againſt the cauſers of our miſeries: but then againe, our conſciences telling us of our owne evill deſervings; we tooke it either for a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14702:21"/>upon us for our former wicked lives; or elſe for an example of Gods mercie, in our wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliverance. Humbling our ſelves therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the mighty hand of <hi>God,</hi> wee caſt downe our ſelves before him in prayer, two or three times a day, which courſe we conſtantly held all the time of our miſery.</p>
            <p>The new yeare now begun, <hi>as the dayes began to lengthen, ſo the cold began to ſtrengthen:</hi> which cold came at laſt to that extremitie, as that it would raiſe bliſters in our fleſh, as if wee had beene burnt with fire: and if wee touch't <hi>iron</hi> at any time, it would ſticke to our fingers like <hi>Bird-lime.</hi> Sometimes if we went but out a-doores to fetch in a little water, the cold would nip us in ſuch ſort, that it made us as ſore as if wee had beene beaten in ſome cruell manner. All the firſt part of the Winter, we found water under the yce, that lay upon the <hi>Bache</hi> on the Sea-ſhoare. Which water iſſued out of an high <hi>Bay</hi> or <hi>Cliffe</hi> of yce, and ranne into the hollow of the <hi>Bache,</hi> there remaining with a thicke yce over it: which yce, wee at one certaine place daily digging through with pick-axes, tooke ſo much water as ſerved for our drinking.</p>
            <p>This continued with us untill the tenth of <hi>Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie:</hi> and then were wee faine to make ſhift with ſnow-water; which we melted by putting hot Irons into it. And this was our drinke untill the twentieth of <hi>May</hi> following.</p>
            <p>By the laſt of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> were the dayes growne to ſome ſeven or eight houres long; and then we again tooke another view of our victuals: which we now
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14702:22"/>found to grow ſo ſhort, that it could no wayes laſt us above ſixe weekes longer. And this bred a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare of famine amongſt us. But our recourſe was in this, as in other our extremities, unto <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God;</hi> who had helps, we knew, though wee ſaw no hopes. And thus ſpent wee our time untill the third of <hi>Februarie.</hi> This proved a marvellous cold day; yet a faire and cleare one: about the middle whereof, all cloudes now quite diſperſed, and nights ſable curtaine drawne; <hi>Aurora</hi> with her golden face ſmiled once againe upon us, at her ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of her bed: for now the glorious Sunne with his glittering beames, began to guild the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt tops of the loftie mountaines. The brightneſſe of the Sunne, and the whiteneſſe of the ſnow, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether was ſuch, as that it was able to have revived even a dying ſpirit. But to make a new addition to our new joy, we might perceive two Beares, (a ſhee one with her Cubbe) now comming towards our Tent: whereupon wee ſtraight arming our ſelves with our lances, iſſued out of the Tent to await her comming. Shee ſoone caſt her greedy eyes upon us; and with full hope of devouring us, ſhee made the more haſte unto us: but with our hearty lances we gave her ſuch a welcome, as that ſhee fell downe upon the ground, tumbling up and downe, and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the very ſnow for anger. Her Cubbe ſeeing this, by flight eſcaped us. The weather now was ſo cold, that longer wee were not able to ſtay abroad: retiring therefore into our Tent, wee firſt warmed our ſelves; and then our againe to draw the dead Beare in unto us. Wee flaied her, cut her into pieces
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14702:22"/>of a <hi>Stone</hi> weight or thereabouts, which ſerv'd us for our dinners. And upon this Beare we fed ſome twenty dayes; for ſhee was very good fleſh, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than our Veniſon. This onely miſchance wee had with her: that upon the eating of her Liver, our very skinnes peeled off: for mine owne part, I being ſicke before, by eating of that Liver, though I loſt my skinne, yet recovered I my health upon it. Shee being ſpent, either wee muſt ſeeke ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate, or elſe fall aboard with our roaſt Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Caske, which we were very loath to doe for feare of famiſhing, if ſo be <hi>that</hi> ſhould be thus ſpent, before the Fleete came out of <hi>England.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid'ſt theſe our feares, it pleaſed God to ſend divers <hi>Beares</hi> unto our Tent; ſome fortie at leaſt, as we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted. Of which number we kill'd ſeven: That is to ſay, the ſecond of <hi>March</hi> one; the fourth, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the tenth, a wonderfull great <hi>Beare,</hi> ſixe foote high at leaſt. All which we flayed and roaſted upon woodden ſpits, (having no better kitchen-fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture than that, and a frying-pan, which we found in the Tent.) They were as good ſavory meate, as any beefe could be. Having thus gotten good ſtore of ſuch foode, wee kept not our ſelves now to ſuch ſtraight allowance as before; but eate frequently two or three meales a-day: which began to increaſe ſtrength and abilitie of body in us.</p>
            <p>By this, the cheerfull dayes ſo faſt increaſed, that the ſeverall ſorts of <hi>Fowles,</hi> which had all the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-time avoy ded thoſe quarters, began now againe to reſort thither, unto their Summer-abiding. The ſixteenth of <hi>March,</hi> one of our two <hi>Maſtive Dogges</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14702:23"/>went out of the Tent from us in the morning: but from that day to this he never more returned to us, nor could wee ever heare what was become of him. The <hi>Fowles</hi> that I before ſpake of, conſtantly uſe every <hi>Spring</hi> time to reſort unto that Coaſt, being uſed to breede there moſt abundantly. Their foode is a certaine kinde of ſmall fiſhes. Yearely upon the abundant comming of theſe <hi>Fowles,</hi> the <hi>Foxes</hi> which had all this Winter kept their Burrowes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Rockes, began now to come abroad, and ſeeke for their livings. For them wee ſet up three <hi>Trappes</hi> like Rat-trappes, and bayted them with the skinnes of theſe <hi>Fowles,</hi> which wee had found upon the ſnow; they falling there in their flight from the hill whereupon they bred, towards the Sea. For this <hi>Fowle,</hi> being about the bigneſſe of a <hi>Ducke,</hi> hath her legs placed ſo cloſe unto her rumpe, as that when they alight once upon the land, they are very hardly (if ever) able to get up againe, by reaſon of the miſplacing of their legs, and the weight of their bodies; but being in the water, they raiſe themſelves with their pinions well enough. After wee had made Theſe Trappes, and ſet them apart one from another in the ſnow, we caught fiftie <hi>Foxes</hi> in them: all which wee roaſted, and found very good meate of them. Then tooke we a Beares skinne, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fleſh ſide upward, wee made Springes of Whales bone, wherewith wee caught about 60. of thoſe <hi>Fowles,</hi> about the bigneſſe of a pigeon.</p>
            <p>Thus continued wee untill the firſt of <hi>May;</hi> and the weather then growing warme; wee were now pretty able to goe abroad to ſeeke for more provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14702:23"/>Every day therefore abroad we went; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could we encounter withall, untill the 24. of <hi>May;</hi> when eſpying a <hi>Bucke,</hi> wee thought to have kill'd him with our Dogge: but he was growne ſo fat and lazie, that hee could not pull downe the Deere. Seeking further out therefore, we found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of <hi>Willocks</hi> egges; (which is a <hi>Fowle</hi> about the bigneſſe of a <hi>Ducke</hi>) of which egges though there were great ſtore, yet wee being but two of us together, brought but thirty of them to the Tent that day; thinking the next day to fetch a thouſand more of them: but the day proved ſo cold, with ſo much <hi>Eaſterly</hi> winde, that wee could not ſtirre out of our Tent.</p>
            <p>Staying at home therefore upon the 25. of <hi>May,</hi> we for that day omitted our ordinary cuſtome. Our order of late (ſince the faire weather) was, every day, or every ſecond day, to goe up to the top of a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, to ſpie if wee could diſcerne the water in the Sea; which untill the day before we had not ſeene. At which time, a ſtorme of winde comming out of the Sea, brake the maine yce within the <hi>Sownd:</hi> after vvhich, the vvinde comming <hi>Eaſterly,</hi> carried all the yce into the Sea, and cleared the <hi>Sownd</hi> a great vvay, although not neere the ſhoare at firſt, ſeeing the cleare vvater came not neere our Tent by three miles at leaſt.</p>
            <p>This 25. of <hi>May</hi> therefore, vvee all day ſtaying in the Tent, there came two Ships of <hi>Hull</hi> into the <hi>Sownd:</hi> vvho knowing that there had been men left there the yeare before; the <hi>Maſter</hi> (full of deſire to know vvhether vve vvere alive or dead) man'd out a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14702:24"/>Shallop from the Ship; with order to row as farre up the <hi>Sownd</hi> as they could, and then to hale up their Shallop, and travell over-land upon the ſnow unto the Tent. Theſe men at their comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, found the Shallop which we had haled from our Tent into the water, with a purpoſe to goe ſeeke ſome Sea-horſes the next faire weather: the Shallop being then already fitted with all neceſſaries for that enterprize. This ſight brought them into a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary; and though this encounter made them hope, yet their admiration made them doubt, that it was not poſſible for us ſtill to remaine alive. Taking therefore our lances out of the Boate, towards the Tent they come; wee never ſo much as perceiving of them: for wee were all gathered together, now about to goe to prayers in the inner Tent; onely <hi>Thomas Ayers</hi> was not yet come in to us out of the greater Tent. The <hi>Hull</hi> men now comming neere our Tent, haled it with the uſuall word of the Sea crying <hi>Hey,</hi> he anſwered againe with <hi>Ho,</hi> which ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den anſwer almoſt amazed them all, cauſing them to ſtand ſtill, halfe afraid at the matter. But we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hearing of them, joyfully came out of the Tent; all blacke as we were with the ſmoake, and with our clothes all tattered with wearing. This uncouth ſight made them further amazed at us: but percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us to be the very men left there all the yeare; with joyfull hearts embracing us, and wee them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, they came with us into our Tent. Comming thus in to us, wee ſhewed them the courteſie of the houſe, and gave them ſuch victuals as we had; which was Veniſon roaſted foure moneths before, and a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14702:24"/>Cuppe of cold water; which for noveltie ſake they kindly accepted of us.</p>
            <p>Then fell wee to aske them what <hi>newes?</hi> and of the ſtate of the Land at home? and when the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Fleete would come? to all which, they returned us the beſt anſwers they could. Agreeing then to leave the Tent; with them wee went to their Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, and ſo a-board the Ship; where we were wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed after the heartieſt and kindeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and there we ſtayed our ſelves untill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>London</hi> Fleete, which we much longed for: hoping by them to heare from our friends in <hi>England.</hi> Wee were told that they would be there the next day; but it was full three dayes ere they came, which ſeemed to us as tedious a three dayes, as any we had yet endured: ſo much we now deſired to heare from our friends, our wives and children.</p>
            <p>The 28. of <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>London</hi> Fleete came into the <hi>Port</hi> to our great comfort. A-board the <hi>Admirall</hi> we went, unto the right noble Captaine, <hi>Captaine Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Goodler,</hi> who is worthy to be honoured by all Sea-men for his courteſie and bounty. This is the Gentleman that is every yeare chiefe Commander of this Fleete; and right worthy he is ſo to be, being a very wiſe man, and an expert Mariner as moſt be in <hi>England,</hi> none diſpraiſed. Unto this Gentleman right welcome we were; and joyfully by him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: hee giving order, that we ſhould have any thing that was in the Ship, that might doe us good, and increaſe our ſtrength; of his owne charges gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us apparell alſo, to the value of twenty pounds worth.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14702:25"/>
            <p>Thus after fourteene dayes of refreſhment, wee grew perfectly well all of us: whereupon the noble Captaine ſent <hi>William Fakely,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Wyſe,</hi> (<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> own Apprentice) and <hi>Thomas Ayers</hi> the Whale-Cutter, with <hi>Robert Good fellow,</hi> unto Maſter <hi>Maſons</hi> Ship, according as themſelves deſired. But thinking there to be as kindly welcomed, as the loſt <hi>Prodigall;</hi> theſe poore men after their enduring of ſo much miſery, which through his meanes partly they had undergone: no ſooner came they a board his ſhip, but he moſt unkindly call'd them <hi>Run-awayes,</hi> with other harſh and unchriſtian termes, farre enough from the civility of an honeſt man. Noble Captaine <hi>Goodler</hi> underſtanding all theſe paſſages, was right ſorie for them, reſolving to ſend for them againe, but that the weather proved ſo bad and uncertaine. I for mine owne part, remained with the Captaine ſtill at <hi>Bottle Cove,</hi> according to mine owne deſire: as for the reſt of us that ſtaid with him, hee preferr'd the <hi>Land-men</hi> to row in the Shallops for the killing of the <hi>Whales;</hi> freeing them thereby from their toyleſome labour a-ſhoare; bettering their <hi>Meanes</hi> beſides. And all theſe favours did this worthy <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> for us.</p>
            <p>Thus were wee well contented now to ſtay there till the twentieth of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> hoping then to returne into our native Countrey: which day of departure being come, and we imbarked, with joyfull hearts we ſet ſayle through the foaming <hi>Ocean,</hi> and though croſſ'd ſometimes with contrary windes homeward bound; yet our proper ſhips at laſt came ſafely to an Anchor in the River of <hi>Thames:</hi> to our great joy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14702:25"/>and comfort, and the Merchants benefite. And thus by the bleſſing of <hi>God</hi> came wee all eight of us well home, ſafe and ſound: where the Worſhipfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie our Maſters, the <hi>Muſcovie</hi> Merchants, have ſince dealt wonderfully well by us. For all which moſt mercifull Preſervation, and moſt wonderfully powerfull Deliverance, all honour, praiſe, and glory by unto the great God, the ſole Author of it. He grant us to make the right uſe of it, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
